Finding Aid for the Paul Iselin Wellman Papers LSC.0140
UCLA Library Special Collections
Paul Iselin Wellman papers
1930-1966
UCLA Library Special Collections
Wellman, Paul Iselin, 1898-1966
LSC.0140
14.5 Linear Feet (29 boxes and 3 oversize boxes)
Paul Iselin Wellman (1898-1966) worked as reporter, writer, and editor for various Wichita newspapers (1919-36) and the Kansas City Star (1936-44) before becoming a screenwriter for Warner Brothers and M-G-M (1944-46). He also wrote histories of the west and many historical novels, including The iron mistress (1951) and The fiery flower (1959). The collection consists of manuscripts, typescripts, and galley proofs of Wellman's screenplays and published books.
Restrictions on Access
Open for research. All requests to access special collections materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
Provenance/Source of Acquisition
Gift of Paul Iselin Wellman, 1949-64.
Gift of Mrs. Paul I. Wellman, 1966-67.
UCLA Catalog Record ID
UCLA Catalog Record ID: 9934672283606533
We are committed to providing ethical, inclusive, and anti-racist description of the materials we steward, and to remediating existing description of our materials that contains language that may be offensive or cause harm. We invite you to submit feedback about how our collections are described, and how they could be described more accurately, by filling out the form located on our website: Report Potentially Offensive Description in Library Special Collections.
Biography
Wellman was born October 14, 1898, in Enid, Oklahoma; AB, Fairmont College (now University of Wichita), 1918; worked as reporter, writer, and editor for various Wichita newspapers, 1919-36, and the Kansas City Star, 1936-44; became a screenwriter for Warner Brothers and M-G-M, 1944-46; published histories of the west and many historical novels, including The iron mistress (1951) and The fiery flower (1959); member, Academy of Motion Picture Arts and Sciences and Society of American Historians; died September 17, 1966 in Los Angeles.
Scope and Content
Collection consists of manuscripts, typescripts, and galley proofs of Wellman's screenplays and published books. Scrapbooks, newspaper clippings, and publicity material for The iron mistress are also included.
Organization and Arrangement
Arranged in the following series:
Manuscripts.
Scrapbooks and newpaper clippings.
Publicity material for The iron mistress.
Indian stories and articles.
Additional Physical Form Available
A copy of the original version of this online finding aid is available at the UCLA Department of Special Collections for in-house consultation and may be obtained for a fee. Please contact:
Public Services Division
UCLA Library, Department of Special Collections
Room A1713, Charles E. Young Research Library
Box 951575
Los Angeles, CA 90095-1575
Telephone: 310/825-4988 (10:00 a.m. - 4:45 p.m., Pacific Time)
Email: spec-coll@library.ucla.edu
Authors, American -- Archives.; Screenwriters -- Archives.; Film scripts.; Western stories.; American fiction -- 20th century.; Wellman, Paul Iselin, 1898-1966--Archives.
- The chain. Garden City, New York: Doubleday, 1949.; 122 sheets. Page proofs (368pp.). Holograph corrections in ink and red crayon. (Box 1)
- The chain. Garden City, New York: Doubleday, 1949.; 123 sheets. Galley proofs. Holograph corrections in blue ink. (Box 1)
- The chain. [Los Angeles, Garden City, New York: Doubleday and Company, 1949., 513 leaves, typescript. Original, double-spaced on 8.5 × 11 paper. Holograph corrections in red crayon and pencil. (Box 1)
- The Comancheros. Los Angeles, A novel. Garden City, New York: Doubleday and Company, 1952., 11 p.l., 236 leaves. Typescript with holograph corrections. (Box 6)
  General note
  Gift of the author, December 1952.
- A dynasty of Western outlaws. [Los Angeles, Garden City, New York: Doubleday and Company, 1961., ca. 1961].; 18 p.l., 401, 46 leaves. 28 cm. Typescript with corrections. (Box 16)
- --- ----., Galley proofs. 3 sets. (Box 16)
- The Female. Los Angeles, Garden City, New York: Doubleday and Company, 1953., 1952-53.; (6 items).
  Scope and Contents note
  A novel of Theodora and Justinian.
  - 1. Typescript no.1., Yellow paper. (Box 8)
  - 2. Typescript no.2., Pink paper. (Box 8)
  - 3. Typescript no.3., Green paper. (Box 9)
  - 4. Typescript no.4., Blue paper. (Box 7)
  - 5. Typescript no.5., White paper. (Box 10)
  - Galley proofs., 170 sheets. (Box 10)
- The fiery flower. Los Angeles, Garden City, New York: Doubleday and Company, ca. 1959. 1961.; 9 p.l., 211 leaves. Typescript with a few holograph corrections; printer's copy. (Box 13)
  A novel.
- --- ---- Another copy., Galley proofs with a few holograph corrections. 82 sheets. (Box 13)
- --- ---- Another copy., Foundry proofs. 99 sheets. (Box 13)
  Gift of the author, December 1959.
- Glory, gold and God. Los Angeles, Garden City, New York: Doubleday and Company, 1954., 529 leaves, typescript. Holograph corrections in ink and red pencil. (Box 7)
- Gold in California. Los Angeles, Boston: Houghton Mifflin, 1958., 82 leaves. Typescript with holograph corrections. (Box 13)
  A history of the Gold Rush. With this: 2 sets of galley proofs with corrections, and a partial set of galleys with the original pencil drawings on the margins by Lorence Bjorkland.
  Gift of the author, November 1958.
- The house divides: the age of Andrew Jackson to Abraham Lincoln. Los Angeles, Garden City, New York: Doubleday and Company, 1966., ca. 1965.; 15 p.l., 663, 52 leaves. 28 cm. Typescript with holograph corrections. (Box 20)
  Mainstream of America series, edited by Lewis Gannett.
  - ---- ----., 5 sets of galleys. (Box 21, Box 22)
    Gift of Mrs. Wellman, October 1966.
- Indian wars and warriors: East. Los Angeles, Boston: Houghton Mifflin, 1959 (North star books: 10)., ca. 1959.; 82 leaves. 28cm. Typescript with holograph corrections. (Box 14)
  Included are proofs of the illustrations by Lorence Bjorklund.
- Indian wars and warriors. II. West of the Mississippi, 1832-1891. Los Angeles, Boston: Houghton Mifflin, 1959 (North star books: 11)., ca. 1959.; 82 leaves. 28cm. Typescript with holograph corrections. (Box 14)
- The Iron Mistress. [Los Angeles, Garden City, New York: Doubleday and Company, 1951
  - 1. Typescript no.1., Yellow paper. (Box 3)
  - 2. Typescript no.2., Yellow paper. (Box 4)
  - 3. Typescript no.3., Yellow paper. (Box 4)
  - 4. Typescript no.4., Blue paper. (Box 5)
  - 5. Final Version., Typescript. (Box 5)
  - 6. Galley proof., 133 leaves. (Box 6)
  - 7. Copy of book, unaccessioned. Garden City, New York, 1951. (Box 6)
  - 8. Miscellaneous publicity material., 7 items. (Box 30)
  - 9. Publicity material., Colored poster in form or book jacket with sheet of instructions for display. (Box 30)
- Jericho's Daughters [Los Angeles, Garden City, New York: Doubleday and Company, 1956.
  Gift of the author, November 1956.
  - 1. Original typescript., 471pp. (Box 2)
  - 2. Galley proofs., 12 leaves. (Box 2)
  - 3. Final proof copy., 378pp. (Box 2)
- Magnificent destiny. [Los Angeles, Garden City, New York: Doubleday, ca. 1962]. 1962.; 11 p.l., 704 leaves. 28 cm. Typescript with corrections. (Box 17)
- --- ---- Galley proofs., 2 sets. (Box 17)
- Portage Bay, Los Angeles, Garden City, New York: Doubleday, 1955-56. 1957.; 2 items.
  - 1. Typescript with holograph corrections., 189 leaves. (Box 11)
  - 2. Page proofs. Marked set., 48 sheets. (Box 11)
- Ride the red earth. Los Angeles, Garden City, New York: Doubleday, 1957-58. 1958.; 4 items.
  Gift of author, August 1958.
  - 1. Typescript with holograph corrections., White paper. 602 leaves. (Box 11)
  - 2. Typescript (carbon). 3rd copy., White paper. 602 leaves. (Box 12)
  - 3. Typescript (carbon). 4th copy., White paper. 602 leaves. (Box 12)
  - 4. Galley proofs., 143 sheets. (Box 11)
- --- ---- Ride the red earth. New York, Bantam Books [, 1959].; 404pp. 17.5 cm. (Box 12)
- Spawn of evil. Los Angeles, Garden City, New York: Doubleday and Company, ca. 1963. 1964.; 449, 32 leaves. 28 cm. Typescript (carbon). (Box 18)
  A history of outlaws on the frontiers of the Ohio and Mississippi valleys between the Revolution and the Civil War.
  This was the copy from which type was set.
- --- ---- Galleys and page proofs., 4 sets. (Box 19)
- Stuart Symington. Portrait of a man with a mission. Los Angeles, Garden City, New York: Doubleday, ca. 1959. 1962.; 256 leaves. 28 cm. Typescript with holograph corrections. (Box 15)
  This is the printer's copy.
- --- ---- Another copy., 93 sheets. Galley proofs. Stamped Nov. 2, 1959. (Box 15)
- --- ---- Another copy., 82 sheets. (283pp.) Page proofs. Stamped Nov. 18, 1959. (Box 15)
- --- ---- Another copy., 95 sheets. (283pp.) Inspection proofs. Printed on green paper. (Box 15)
- Wellman, Paul Iselin, 1898-1966. The ageless story of Peter Schlemihl, by ... and Robert Thoeren. n.p., Publishing history unknown., 102 leaves. Typescript. (Box 23)
- --- Cheyenne. [Los Angeles], 1944.; 63 leaves. (Box 23)
  Brief story synopsis and cast of characters.
- --- Anothor copy. [Los Angeles], 1944.; Typescript (carbon). (Box 23)
- --- Cheyenne. [Los Angeles], 1944.; 175 leaves. (Box 23)
- --- Another copy, [Los Angeles], 1944.; Revised draft. 175 leaves. (Box 23)
- --- Another copy. [Los Angeles], 1944.; 175 leaves. Typescript (carbon). (Box 23)
- Andrews, Robert D. Copper camp. [Los Angeles], 1905.; 27 leaves. Script. Typescript (carbon). (Box 23)
- Wellman, Paul Iselin, 1898-1966. The fiery flower. n,p., Garden City, New York: Doubleday, n.d. 1961.; 211 leaves. Typescript (carbon). (Box 23)
- --- The forty-niners., August 29, 1906.; 129 leaves. Typescript (carbon). (Box 23)
  A story.
- --- Another copy., 129 leaves. Typescript. (Box 23)
- --- Another copy., 129 leaves. Typescript (carbon). (Box 23)
- --- Another copy., 126 leaves. Typescript (carbon). Screenplay. (Box 23)
- --- Another copy. Fragments, 47 leaves. Typescript (carbon). Screenplay. (Box 23)
- --- The Buckstones. n.p., Publishing history unknown., 1966.; 459 leaves. Typescript. (Box 24)
- --- Another copy., 459 leaves. Typescript (carbon). (Box 24)
- --- Another copy. Fragments., 97 leaves. Typescript. (Box 24)
- --- The Buckstones. n.p., New York: Triedent Press, December 1, 1966. 1967.; 166 leaves. Typescript. (Box 25)
  A novel. Author's corrections on raster.
- -- The Passage of Prudence Buckstone. n.p., n.d.; 19 leaves. Typescript (carbon). (Box 25)
  Outline of a novel.
- --- The Buckstones. Trident Press, New York, 1967; 488pp. (Box 25)
  A novel. Unrevised, uncorrected advance proofs.
- --- The Buckstones., 44 leaves. Typescript (carbon). (Box 25)
  Fragment of a novel: Old pages and revised ending.
- --- The Buckstones., 20 leaves. (Box 25)
- --- The Buckstones. n.p., n.d.; 549 leaves. Typescript. (Box 25)
  A novel. Original copy-edited manuscript.
- --- The Passage of Prudence Buckstone. n.p., n.d.; 471 leaves. Typescript (carbon). (Box 26)
- --- Another copy. n.p., n.d.; 405 leaves. Yellow page draft. Typescript. (Box 26)
- The forty-niners. n.p., Garden City, New York: Doubleday and Company, 1946. 1961.; 129 leaves. Typescript (carbon). (Box 27)
- ---The forty-niners. n.p., 1946.; 39 leaves. Typescript (carbon). (Box 27)
  Ship sketches-- data.
- ---The kissing bandit. n.p., January 28, 1946.; 80 leaves. Typescript (carbon). (Box 27)
  A screenplay.
- ---The kissing bandit: suggested story-line. n.p., March 26, 1946.; 11 leaves. Typescript (carbon). (Box 27)
  A story for the screenplay.
- --- Another copy. n.p., March 26, 1946.; 11 leaves. Typescript (carbon). (Box 27)
- ---The kissing bandit: story-line. n.p., April 24, 1946.; 22 leaves. Typescript (carbon). (Box 27)
- ---The kissing bandit n.p., May 14, 1946.; 95 leaves. Typescript (carbon). (Box 27)
- ---The Prodigal judge. n.p., April 6, 1946.; 43 leaves. Typescript (carbon). (Box 27)
  Dialogue Treatment for a screenplay.
- --- Another copy. n.p., April 6, 1946.; 43 leaves. Typescript (carbon). (Box 27)
- ---Red Gold (Treatment). n.p., March 1, 1945.; Typescript. 135 leaves. (Box 27)
  Story for the screenplay.
- --- Another copy. n.p., March 1, 1945.; 135 leaves. (Box 27)
- ---Red Gold (Treatment). n.p., May 29, 1945.; 137 leaves. Typescript. (Box 27)
- ---Red Gold (Treatment). n.p., May 29, 1945.; 137 leaves. Typescript. (Box 28)
- --- Another copy. n.p., May 29, 1945.; 137 leaves. Typescript. (Box 28)
- ---Henry Russel Sanders. Los Angeles., August 18, 1953. (Box 28)
  A booklet: a eulogy for Coach Sanders, by P.I.W.
- ---Savage Altars, n.p., n.d.; 112 leaves. Typescript (carbon). (Box 28)
  A radio play.
- --- Newspaper clippings from the Wichita Eagle,, relating to the Savage Altars radio play., January 1, 1933 (Box 28)
- --- Untitled novel, n.p., n.d.; Typescript (carbon) 26 leaves. (Box 28)
  Outline of a theme and plot for a novel.
- ---Yonder lies my valley. n.p., 88 leaves. Typescript (carbon). (Box 28)
  A musical play.
- --- Walls of Jericho. n.p., New York: A.B. Lippincott company, n.d. c. 1947.; 601 leaves. Typescript. (Box 28)
  A novel, original manuscript.
- --- Scrapbooks (2), containing nemeparer clippings of a general nature from, by or about Favl Wellman., 1932-1945? (Box 29)
- --- The life and times of Bill Ackerman. Los Angeles,, written for a testimonial dinner., May 6, 1961 (Box 29)
- Ephemera. Various newspaper clippings,, presumably by or about Paul Wellman., 1938?-1952? (Box 29)
- Publicity material for The Iron Mistress - poster of dustjacket with instructions for display. (Box 30)
- Indian stories written for Wichita Eagle, 1930-1932.; [Newspaper copies]. (Box 31)
- Indian articles written for The Town Crier (Sunday magazine), The Whichita Beacon, 1926-1928. (Box 32)